Hey everyone, welcome back, welcome to another exciting video
and in this video, we are going to make our own video subtitle generator app using AI
so basically what we are going to achieve in this video is
if we have a video, let's say like you watch my videos and those videos are in Hindi language
so what I want is that I have an AI tool to process my videos
and generate subtitles in English language
so that non-Hindi speakers can also watch my videos by reading subtitles
so just to set the context first, if you have watched my live stream video yesterday
then I have given you this challenge that if you can make this, it will be really cool
so like this is a real problem that all the content creators face and I personally face
and all the online tools like capwing, wheat are very expensive
so I thought let's make our own and make a video or a tutorial that how I made this
so let's start with the video
before starting the video, let's take an overview of what we are going to do
how we are going to approach this
so basically what we are going to do is we are going to use docker
so we have a docker container
what we are going to do is we are going to use Ubuntu image in this
we are going to install some tools in this
so what we are going to do is we are going to install some video file in docker container
and in return what we are going to do is we are going to make a text file
a text file and an SRT file
in which our transcriptions and I can say our subtitles will be there
and it can be that whatever we are going to do in the video is in any language
like Hindi, Punjabi or any language
and in return what we are going to do is we are going to generate subtitles in English language
so this is our approach
and for this what we are going to do is we are going to use whisper AI
so if you don't know what is whisper AI
whisper AI is basically a large language model
that works on videos or on audios
and this is completely open source
and free of cost
so if you want to read its architecture
then you can read it here
so in this you can see that if the user says this
then you can generate English transcriptions
you can generate any to English transcriptions
for example the user is talking in any language
and the transcriptions that are being made are in English language
and this is exactly what we want
so let's start from the coding part
I didn't want to waste much time here
so we are going to use this and this is free of cost
so for this video tutorial
I have recorded a sample video here
this is in Hindi language
so let me show you the video
so let me play it
welcome
so this is a sample video
which is going to be in Hindi
and we will try to generate subtitles
of this Hindi video
in English language
so that our non-Hindi speaking audience
can enjoy this video
so let's see
how our English subtitles
come out
so this is our video
which we are going to translate
so let's do one thing
let's open our terminal
this is our terminal
and we will make a new project
in the coding folder
so we will call it video translator
so this is our server video translator
and in this I will do cd
video translator
and code dot
which will open my vscode
so as per our architecture
we need to make a docker container
so let's do one thing
let's make a docker file
and just in case you don't know docker
you never worked with docker
so what you can do is you can just head over
to learn.pushkar.dev
and you can just get at my course of docker
I will put the link in the description
so here is the course
so in this we have covered
the docker from absolute beginner
to advanced level
but please consider this course
so you can see this course
back to the topic
so what we are going to do
I will assume that you already know docker
so what we are going to do is
we will take a base image here first
as I told you
we will take a base image here
what it means is that we will do it inside
now we have to use this whisper ai
it is very simple
what we have to do is
first we have to install the whisper ai
so that is we have to install pip
which is ok
after that what we have to do is
we have to install some tools here
just like ffmpeg
so internally we have to use ffmpeg
and we have to install ffmpeg
inside our docker container
and we have to install this too
after that that's it
we are ready to go
after that you can see what we have to do
we have to say whisper
whatever audio video file we have to give
it will be in hindi language
and we will say
task translate
so what it will do is translate it in english
if we don't give this task
then what it will do is
the language in which we have this video
will generate the same subtitles
what we can do is we can make two translations
we can make hindi subtitles
and we can make english subtitles
so this is going to be really cool
so let's start it quickly
so what we have to do is
finally we want to do a command run
that is apt update
so our packages will be updated
and after that what we are going to do is
we are going to do apt install ffmpeg
so what we have to do inside this docker container
we have to install ffmpeg
plus we have to install python
so here you can quickly search
like python install
in ubuntu
so how we can install python
so let's see in documentation
after apt update
we just have to run this command
and python will be installed
we can say and and python 3
and similarly we will install
pip install in ubuntu
so we can see
how we can install pip
so we just have to write apt install this thing
so here I can say and and this
and make sure
that we have a command of hyphen y
or else it will ask us
if we have to install it or not
so as soon as we
run this thing our packages are installed
now what we have to do is
we have to install visper ai
inside our machine
so I will do this command copy
and we will do run and this
so what will it do? it will install
my open ai visper
inside my docker container
and after that we will run
so we will say run and this
that's it our visper ai setup is done
now we will say entry point
and here we will say bash
if you run this container
then it will run from bash
ideally we should run visper
but I want to show you
how things work so here we can
keep it bash
now make sure that your docker demon is running
so till this point my docker demon
was still closed so I just run
docker demon
so you can see that my docker is running
so docker is now running
so now we just have to write a command
then I will say build
tag
and we will say my visper
okay we can name it
and dot
dot means the path where this docker file is
and enter
now this thing will take some time because
it will first fetch ubuntu and then
install all these things and then our
container will be built
which we can use for our translations
so this thing is going to take a lot of time
because ubuntu
you can see that ubuntu is getting
pulled if you already have ubuntu
right if you already have ubuntu
pulled then it will not take that much time
but because this is my first time
pulling this so it is taking time
so it's okay we can wait
so we wait on this
cool so now you can see that our docker
is set up if I come back
then you will see that we have an image
that is my visper
so this is our custom image that we just made
now we can use it
here my desktop
if I go to my terminal
and I do a series
dot dot
so here if I go to my desktop
okay so what I will do here quickly
I will make a folder on the desktop
which I will name it sample
samples
so I know that you cannot see
this particular thing
so here if I do ls then you will see that
here we have a folder sample
so if I do cd in sample
so here this is our file
which we have to translate
right so in this file
let's rename this file
we will call it sample.mov
so if I do ls again
you can see that this is our MOV file
which I showed you just now
so now what we can do is we just have to run our container
so what I will do is
first we copy this file path
so this is the file
so here we right click get info
so first we copy this file
so I have done this copy
so here we will do docker run
interactive
volume mapping
okay I hope that you can see the command
I will zoom in also
okay volume mapping
so you map this volume
slash home slash videos
and after that we have to run which container
that is mywhisper
so my-whisper
so this was our container
so we will run it and enter
this is our container up and running
if you do ls and I go to
cd-home
and in cd-home I go to
and I can go to like
you can see that here we can go
in videos if I do ls
then you can see that in our container
I am able to access that file
so what we have to do is we just have to write
whisper here
our file name sample.mov
and after that we will mention that
which is our language
so these are the examples and in which you can see
Hindi is also included okay these are the languages
so here I can say hyphen hyphen language
okay hyphen hyphen language
that is Hindi with a capital H
then we will call it task
so everything is translated from documentation
so as soon as I do this
and I will press enter
now this thing is going to take a lot of time
the reason being is because we
basically what happens is because this is an AI
so AI models need GPU
and my machine is not having
GPU okay so it works
very slow on CPU
but in reality obviously you will deploy this thing
on a cloud okay so we will deploy it on a cloud
so we should have
GPU instances there but okay for this
demonstration you can try this way
if you have GPU then this thing is going to be very fast
but if your machine doesn't have GPU
then this thing is going to be slow
so now you can see that
how our subtitles are
and it really took just one minute
okay so here you can see
yes welcome so this is a sample video
which is going to be in
in shudh hindi and we will try that
so if you will look carefully
what he did, he gave me this MOV
file which I will tell you again
so it was in Hindi right if I play it again
yes welcome
so this is a sample video
which is going to be in shudh hindi
and we will try that
we can generate subtitles of this shudh hindi video
in English language
so that our non-hindi
speaking audience can enjoy this video
so let's see
how our English subtitles
come out
right so you can see that
he did a very good job
and what he did in return
he did some sample videos right you can see that
if I open this json okay open with
vs code so you can see that if I
format this document so you can see that
what he did he said that
from 0 to 2 you said yes welcome
so this is a timestamp okay
so this is a sample video and it started
at this time and ended at this time
so if you can do it through any video
processing you can put subtitles on it
okay here one more thing that I want
to do is if I can just attach
the subtitles here itself
because if you have seen carefully
we also have srt file
we also have vtt file
so what are these vtt files
these are basically our translation files
so you can see that as it is
you can upload it on youtube
automatically it will make subtitles
so here if I go to my quicktime player
I am not sure if we can
do this for subtitles
so here like option should be
subtitles are like none okay
so let's do one thing let's go to chrome
okay so here I will say that
let's say we open any service
let's say maybe weed okay so let's open
weed.io so here
I upload the video first okay
by the way weed.io is a
like AI tool so here we will upload
so in the desktop
in the sample we will open it
okay so let's open this thing
let's open it here
here I will go to subtitles
so here I will say manual okay here
we can upload our own file so upload
okay and here I will say that
to upload
Hindi is okay import
so to import what we have to give
we have to give srt file
what it was like
let's go back so it says
that yeah so we can upload srt file
so let's upload this file
okay I didn't do anything I
uploaded the file that our AI generated
now let's play it
welcome
so this is a sample video which will be
in pure Hindi and we will try
that we can generate subtitles
of this pure Hindi video
in English language
so that our non-hindi speaking audience
can enjoy this video
so let's see that this video
how our English subtitles
come out
so as you have already seen
that we were able to
generate subtitles
that is also free of cost
so we used whisper here
and for this video
it is a very short video in which
I wanted to show you how you can achieve this
particular thing and now what I am planning
is that I will make a web application
in which we will do this on cloud
so what you can do is like you can connect
because obviously these things are coming
like this will charge you money because
one CPU is running on the cloud
so like you can upload a video
you can pay the money and then
the subtitles will come out in different languages
so this thing was that simple to do
and I hope you enjoyed the video
if you liked the video then like and subscribe
do tell in the comments how did you like the video
see you in the next video
until then bye bye take care